Before we continue, I want to let you know
that for future print statements, I am not
going to verbalize every character I am typing.
I will call out what I am typing and then
type it and let you look over what has been
added to the code.
Whereas indexing extracts a value from a list,
slicing extracts characters from a list, word,
or phrase.
For our slicing examples, I have the 123-slicing
file open, and we have, on line 1, a variable
called serialnumber, a series of sixteen numbers,
with dashes between every four numbers.
Each set of four numbers has some significance,
so we will see how to extract the first four
numbers, the eight numbers in the middle with
the dash, and the last four numbers.
Games may contain codes that have some of
the characters mean something, like a player
status or something similar, so knowing how
to slice a value will save one from having
to do it elsewhere, like in Excel, thus saving
time and potential chance for errors within
an app.
On line 2, I will add a print function to
output the first four characters from the
serial_number variable.
The slice is contained after the value and
in square brackets.
Then, the start and end characters are separated
with a colon, though only a start or end needs
to be specified.
Thus, I will type a colon and then 4 to represent
that I want a slice starting at the beginning
of the string and then continuing for four
characters.
When I run this code, we get the first four
serial number characters.
If you think a colon and 4 give us the first
four characters, what will happen if we reverse
the slice and start with a 4 and then a colon?
Let’s find out.
I will copy the print statement on line two
to line three, make that change, and then
run the code again.
Did you expect to see this result?
You may have thought that maybe you want to
see the last four characters, but this slice
starts after character four.
Let me repeat the key word: after.
Remember that Python is zero-based, so technically,
we are beginning the slice on the fifth character,
the first dash.
And with nothing after the colon, we are telling
the slice to slice everything to the end of
the value.